Wow,
a lot of people here.
Mhm.
>> Good afternoon and welcome to the
January 5th, 2026 public services
committee. Um I would ask that anyone in
the room silence your phone or your
electronics if you could please. Uh we
have one item on the agenda today.
That's the only thing we'll be
considering. No, no walk-ons for the
committee.
Um if you'd like to speak to the group,
we'll have a open discussion both online
and uh in person. With that, uh
Jennifer, could we have a first item,
please?
>> Number nine, ordinance, second reading,
creating chapter 1.28, 28 administrative
inspection warrants establishing
authority for their issuance and
amending the municipal code of the city
of Cheyenne, Wyoming to authorize
certain city officials as specified to
apply for administration administrative
inspection warrants.
>> And could we have a staff report,
please?
>> Good afternoon, Chairman. David
Hopinson, deputy city attorney. Welcome.
>> Um, I was just going to give kind of a
brief overview about inspection warrants
generally and I would defer kind of the
policy to the uh the chief building
official or uh the fire chief to speak
to the uh the committee as far as the
need for the ordinance. But what this
ordinance uh just briefly does is it
allows or puts into code um and allows
the chief fire
uh or the chief of the fire department
and the uh chief building official to
seek administrative inspection warrants.
Uh and the kind of the purpose for that
is to allow them when there's a need for
the enforcement of municipal code or
state law uh that's administrative in
nature as opposed to criminal in nature.
it kind of creates the framework for
that. Uh really just brief history kind
of prior to 1967
um
uh code enforcement or code officials
had a lot more leeway as far as being
able to go on to properties for
inspection purposes. Uh the Supreme
Court in that year uh held that, you
know, you can't do that. There's still
got to be some framework even though the
standard might be lower. And so what
they kind of ended up with are what we
call administrative inspection warrants
which have a lower standard of proof or
or cause rather uh with respect to
entering into a person's property uh
primarily because the nature of uh the
inspection is not criminal. It's simply
to enforce uh municipal code and
ordinance. it has lower requirements in
that sense. Uh as well as
allowing them when it's reasonable
legislative or administrative standards
for conducting kind of routine
inspections are in place or if they do
have probable cause, they could still
get in uh or authorize a warrant under
that
standard or if the inspection is
reasonably necessary to determine,
discover or verify the condition of a
property. Um, so in that sense, it's a
little bit easier to get this kind of
warrant, but also the consequences for
people are less than than you would see
under a criminal standard. I'm happy to
speak more about that. Happy to dive
down into the details of the the
ordinance as as the committee seeks, but
otherwise would stand for questions.
>> Thank you, David. Questions from the
committee for staff. Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Um, can you just
give me an example of when we would use
this?
>> Sure. So, um, I think one of the
kind of genesis for for this stems from,
you know, if there's an abandoned
property, uh, and they we can't locate
the owner, but the city wants to make
sure that there's nobody in there before
they go in and take steps to to board it
up, that things of that nature. Uh, this
would be in place to allow them to go to
municipal court and say, "Hey, got this
property. we've tried to locate the
owner, can't locate the owner. Um, but
here's why we think, you know, this
building is in violation of of code or
is unsafe. Um, and we need to go in
there, make sure nobody's there, and
then take the steps to protect the
community. So, a circumstance like that
be one that this would allow for
>> Dr. Aldridge. Chairman Crave for you.
So, if we had an individual um who had a
property that had been red tagged um
many months ago and the building
inspector has basically said, "This
property needs to be inspected before
you're able to move forward um and do
any more work on this property." And
we've had no response from that
individual. Um some underage drinking
parties going on there, people living in
that property. Would this type of
administrative warrant then allow the
building inspector to be able to gain
access to that property to inspect it?
Um because re work is continuing on even
though it's red tagged.
>> Uh so potentially yes. You know they
they still have the requirement to seek
out consent. That's one thing that this
does require prior to getting a warrant.
They have to seek consent. if they can't
obtain consent, but they still have uh
kind of those other things such as, you
know, if there's a clear uh
administrative standard or or kind of
routine periodic or area inspection
standard, they could get in under that
and get the warrant on those grounds.
Um, you know, or if it's reasonably
necessary to determine, discover, or
verify that condition of the property
and their compliance with the code, they
could get in under that as well. Uh, so
yes, that is a circumstance that this
may apply to. Thank you,
>> Councilman White. Any questions for
staff?
>> No, I don't have any questions. I think
Dr. Aldridge um asked a question that
gave me more information. So, thank you.
>> All right. Thank you, sir. Appreciate
it. We'll open it up for public comment.
Uh is there anyone in the room or um
online that would like to speak to us?
Chief
>> Chair, Chief Dyhorn, um with Cheyenne
Fire Rescue. Um just to to kind of
elaborate on some of that from the from
the fire and emergency services side. Um
we we want to provide this
constitutional process basically. Um
we're always very very willing to work
with homeowners, business owners. Um and
it and it often works well and we gain
consent. Um but we do have some some
areas of difficulty sometimes whether
it's investigating fires or inspecting
uh buildings. So um this just gives our
our folks a tool um to go back to um
gives them clear reason to be there. We
are explaining that to the the the owner
of the residence or the business of why
we're there. Um it's very specific in in
what we're doing there as well. Um
there's sometimes a gray area where
especially investigating fires where we
may not know if we have probable cause
for a criminal search warrant and so we
don't have a tool right now to rely on.
So if the if the the property owner
doesn't want to give us that consent
then we're we're kind of stuck right
now. Um we we do very well to work with
with our community and our citizens to
to to gain that consent and we will
continue to do that. Um, but there's a
lot of case law with with the fire
service and um, again, we just want to
make sure we're not violating anybody's
Fourth Amendment rights um, with this
type of language and we want to make
sure that there's a clear and present
operational policy for our department to
pursue some of these things. Um, further
to kind of answer your questions from
examples from the fire department side,
when we're on scene, uh, in an
emergency, uh, we're there and we can do
whatever we need to on the property.
It's when we leave that property is when
we often have issues of we have to come
back and do more investigation, things
like that, collect evidence. Um, and
that's when we gain that consent from
the property owner typically. Um, this
can also happen though when we're trying
to enforce code or inspect properties
that people may not want us to go into a
certain part of their building for
whatever the reason. Um, and so this
will give us that tool if they weren't
willing to work with us. We've had we've
had a few instances over the years. Um,
again, talking with the city attorney's
office, you know, we were talking about,
you know, how often will this process be
used? Um, we don't we don't think it
will be that that often. Um, but at
least it is a tool to to go to a judge
and ask for a sworn affidavit that we
would like this administrative search
warrant. And I would stand for any
questions if you guys have any chief.
Dr.
>> Chairman Crave through you. I was I'm
just wondering what have we
because I'm guessing and knowing that we
there have been properties we've had to
um access in order to board up and
things like that where we might not have
been able to reach the homeowner or the
land owner. Um have we just been doing
these basically without consent up to
this point um when we it was necessary
to be able to access the property?
>> Um no. We typically pause and and try to
gain who who the property owner is, get
a hold of them. Um we just had one
recently down on First and Mory where we
had trouble getting hold of the property
owner. Um but some abandoned buildings
had had been burned. Um we went back
there the next morning to kind of survey
the damage and figure out if there was
anything else needed. Um something was
still actually smoldering which caused
us to call a crew back. Um, so again, it
constituted an emergency where we could
actually go back onto the property and
and do that. So, um, but no, typically
we again we we try to pause and delay
that stuff. Sometimes it it is difficult
to get a home of property owners if
they're not if they're not local or
they're, you know, just just don't want
to talk to us sometimes about their
property. So, that can be difficult.
But, we do try to make sure that we we
get consent. We're not just out there
trespassing. And you know, it depends on
what we're trying to do as well. If we
can do it with a, you know, a potential
drone or taking pictures on the outside
of the perimeter of a property, maybe
that helps, too.
>> That that was going to be my next
question. Chairman Crave, do we have any
other tools that would could be utilized
in place of this administrative warrant
in order to gain access?
>> Legally speaking,
>> well, preferably, yes. or or hardware
speaking like we we do have we do have
tools as far as as drones and things
like that but even that is I I would
defer again to the attorney's office of
where some of that you know evidence
quote unquote of gathering information
off somebody's property could be maybe
thrown out or or a fourth amendment
right violation. So we need to be
careful with those unmanned aerial
devices as well. So
>> that's my understanding as well is that
with drones that there is a state
statute that's been passed in recently
in the last few years that does limit
the access we have for drone footage.
>> Sure. And and state statute really leans
us instead and states that our
department's responsible for doing these
things, but it doesn't give us the tool
to actually do it as well as the fire
code. Um it states we should follow an
administrative warrant procedure which
we don't have. So again we we kind of
raised our hands to be included in this
ordinance for that reason. Thank you,
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. So, this is
specific to a fire concern, not a
nuisance concern, not a law enforcement.
It's just specific to fire. Is that
correct? I
>> I believe it's both. So, it can be for
the chief building official and and what
uh Mr. Hopinson described as well as far
as a nuisance building, things like
that. If it's a dangerous building, um,
we work in strict collaboration with the
building official to kind of determine
next steps. Um, depending if there's
combustible material there, if there's
hazardous materials there, we we have to
gauge each one of these properties kind
of kind of one by one. So, um, it does
it does encompass both the fire
department and and the building
department.
>> So, if I could follow up just for my
clarification. So if Tono had a concern
about something,
he could also use this process.
>> Yes. Okay. As far as my understanding.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Thank you.
>> Councilman White, any uh questions?
>> Um, no, sir. I I would just point out
that I appreciate uh Chief Daicorn's
uh testimony and it's very timely
because um this past Saturday we had a
ward one counsel and coffee and we had I
had a constituent show me pictures of a
house in West Cheyenne with a collapsed
chimney and um it's it's been vacant
abandoned for years and so um I'm
actually going to forward the
photographs over to Director Fountain
and Chief uh and the chief uh because
to me it certainly looks like a
potentially dangerous situation. And so,
um, I think I think giving this tool to
our staff is, uh, very important and I
think they've certainly done all their
due diligence with regard to, uh, making
sure all rights, uh, from the property
owners are are being maintained.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Chief. Any other
uh, public comments? Yes, sir. David.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. I just wanted
to clarify one thing about how it's
currently drafted. It generally doesn't
apply to what you can might think of as
the nuisance statutes or code itself. Uh
things like, you know, if your grass is
too long, that sort of thing. This isn't
going to apply to that. Uh it's more
with respect to the kind of where the
building chief comes in. It's it's more
the permitting, that sort of thing. Uh
you know, with the building code itself.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Chairman Crave, I just had a question
for our assistant city attorney.
Would would in your opinion is this
really a public safety uh issue more
than a compliance issue?
>> With I guess with respect to to that
particular question, um that kind of
gets into policy more than what it
really does. So, I I think a lot of the
genesis of it certainly stems from
public safety. Um, but could it as
drafted be used for enforcement of the
building codes? Absolutely. Um, so I
guess it kind of covers both, but I
think that the purpose behind it or or
kind of why it's it's before the
committee is is more geared towards that
safety concern.
>> I would like to think that our building
codes are based on public safety needs.
So,
>> thank you.
Thank you. Is there anyone else uh in
the room or online that would like to
make a public comment? Jennifer,
anybody?
>> No hands raised. Last chance. All right.
Could we have a motion, please?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to approve in a second.
Discussion by the committee.
>> Discussion.
>> Councilman White. Anything?
>> No. No, sir.
>> All right. All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> I. I
>> opposed. The recommendation for Monday
night will be to approve. That's the end
of our agenda. Thank you very much.